在任何生态系统中
In any ecosystem,
你都能发现捕食者与猎物之间那微妙的平衡
you'll find a delicate balance between predator and prey.
某些知名的捕食者
Some well-known predators
以下动物名用的都是拉丁文学名
比如狮
include Panthera leo,
棕熊
Ursus arctos,
以及1987年电影《铁血战士》的主角
and star of the 1987 film Predator,
铁血战士[捕食者]
Predator.
而猎物的例子呢
Now, examples of prey
包含了穴兔
include oryctolagus cuniculus,
鸡
Gallus gallus domesticus,
还有个26.3公斤  浑身湿透的
and weighing in at 58 pounds soaking wet,
小型新人
Diminutive homo novus--
而且奇特的是
curiously, a close relative
他还跟鸡[懦夫]是近亲
of Gallus gallus domesticus.
库珀
Cooper.
你的站到了
Your stop.
能麻烦您在离我家近点的地方再放我下吗
Would you mind dropping me off closer to my house?
你知道按规定我不可以这样的吧
You know I'm not allowed to do that.
如果我帮忙你报税呢
What if I did your taxes?
抱歉啦  孩子
Sorry, kiddo.
本来我可以帮你弄到很不错的退税呢
I could've gotten you a nice refund.
从下车点到我家正门口的危险旅程
The perilous journey from the bus stop to my front door
有足足97.5米
was 97.5 meters.
顺带一提  在保守的老家德州东部
FYI, insisting on using the metric system
不使用美制度量标准也是我被人猎杀的原因之一
in East Texas is another reason I was hunted by predators.
新人需要来一罐巧克力饮料
Homo novus needs a Yoo-hoo.
♪ 世上没人比我强壮 ♪
♪ Nobody else is stronger than I am ♪
♪ 昨天我移了一座山 ♪
♪ Yesterday I moved a mountain ♪
♪ 我相信我能当你的英雄 ♪
♪ I bet I could be your hero ♪
♪ 我是个了不起的小家伙 ♪
♪ I am a mighty little man ♪
少
年
谢尔顿
柔道
Jiu-jitsu?
我决定学习防身术
I've decided to learn self-defense.
-为什么  -因为我个子小
- Why? - I'm quite small,
而且还得小个几年
and will be for several years,
如果我发育晚  甚至得小更多年
maybe even more if I'm a late bloomer.
你爸爸人高马大  或许你会遗传到这点
Your dad's big, maybe you'll take after him.
我们都爱我妈
We both like my mom.
我跟他之间的共同点就这么多了
I think that's where the similarities end.
跟你说啊  其中一本书里有提到
You know, one of the books mentioned
一种越南武术
a Vietnamese martial art.
越武道  我是蓝带了
Vovinam. I'm a blue belt.
没什么好震惊的
Don't be impressed.
你妈帮你买一件制服你就是蓝带了
It's what you get when your mom buys the uniform.
你还记得那功夫吗
Do you remember any of it?
我连那带子在那里都忘了
I don't even know where the belt is.
书上说柔道
The book says jiu-jitsu
靠的就是以柔克刚  借力使力
is based on using your attacker's momentum against them.
这只是物理学  冲我来
It's just physics. Come at me.
向你冲刺吗
Like, run at you?
我还是新手  你就快步向我来就好了
Well, I'm new to this, so maybe just walk quickly.
当我走到时呢
And what happens when I get to you?
我会利用你的惯性来放倒你
I'll use your inertia to take you down.
行吧
Okay.
惯性什么时候会把我放倒
And when does inertia take me down?
随时都可能
Any second.
我不懂了
I don't understand.
我利用了物理学啊
I'm using physics.
这个锁脚的关节技名叫外足缄[比赛禁用]
This leg lock is called an Outside Ashi Garami.
接下来呢
What happens next?
这得看了  这是你的脚还是我的脚
That depends, is this your foot or mine?
库珀  你的站
Cooper. Your stop.
我昨晚保龄球打了新高分
I bowled a new high score last night.
厉害
Nice.
-我打了两次火鸡  -什么是火鸡
- I got two turkeys. - What's a turkey?
连续三次全倒
It's three strikes in a row.
为什么会把这样取名叫火鸡啊
Why do they call it a turkey?
当保龄球游戏刚发明的时候
Well, when they first invented bowling,
人们是用冷冻的火鸡肉来打倒球瓶
they used to just throw frozen turkeys at the pins.
后来才变成了用保龄球
Eventually, they switched to balls
来减少球场的味道
to cut down on the smell.
你为什么要骗她
Why you lying to her?
我发现这样能让我脑筋保持灵活
I find it keeps my mind sharp.
谢尔顿  吃早饭啦
Sheldon, breakfast!
马上来
Be right there!
谢尔顿
Sheldon!
来了
Coming!
大家早
Hello.
谢利  你还好吗
Shelly, you all right?
还好啊
Yes.
可能是因为
I must be a little sore
昨天跟丹对练柔道  所以有点浑身酸痛
from doing jiu-jitsu with Tam yesterday.
你们为什么要玩柔道
Why were you doing jiu-jitsu?
我们是男生啊  男生就爱打闹
We're boys. Roughhousing is what we do.
-那是什么  -什么什么
- What was that? - What was what?
那个声音
That sound.
什么声音
What sound?
这是什么
What's all this?
一层额外的保护层
An extra layer of protection.
保护什么
Protection from what?
亲爱的  有人欺负你吗
Sweetie, is someone bothering you?
-有  -是谁
- Yes. - Who is it?
我不想说
I'd rather not talk about it.
不行  我现在就要知道是谁
No, I want a name right now.
玛丽
Mary.
你有欺负他吗
Have you been hurting him?
我只用我的语言欺负
Only with my words.
谢利  告诉我是谁欺负你
Tell me who it is, Shelly.
玛丽  你冷静点
Mary, slow down.
你别叫我冷静
Don't tell me to slow down.
有人欺负他
Someone is bullying him.
行  行
Okay. Okay.
谢尔顿  你不能穿成这样去上学
Sheldon, you can't go to school wearing all that.
回房间把它脱下来
Go to your room and take it off.
遵命
Yes, sir.
你去帮忙他
You go with him.
但我的麦片快要泡糊了
But my cereal's gonna get soggy.
去
Go.
我就想有个清静的早晨
I'd like one nice morning.
为什么这事情你都不生气的
Why aren't you more upset about this?
我不高兴啊  但是我们应该小心处理
I am. I just think we should proceed with caution.
-有人在伤害我们儿子  -我知道
- Someone is hurting our son. - I understand.
但处理恶霸的事很复杂
But handling bullies is tricky. It...
很容易弄巧成拙  害他更惨
It's easy to make things worse.
这事情你还是什么专家吗
And what makes you the expert?
亲爱的  我当年就是恶霸
Honey, I was a bully.
他说得对
He's right.
你用错误的方式插手此事
You get involved in this in the wrong way,
恶霸们就会在谢尔顿身上发泄
and they'll take it out on Sheldon.
抱歉啊  但我就是没办法不作为
Well, I'm sorry, but I can't just stand by.
小乔治  我有事情要跟你说  你也该起床了
Georgie, I need to talk to you, and wake up,
你会来不及的
you're gonna be late.
放心  我换好衣服才睡的
Got it covered. I slept in my clothes.
天啊  你听我说  有人在欺负你弟弟
Oh, Lord. Look, somebody has been picking on your brother.
你知道这事情吗
You know anything about it?
不知道
No.
你最好不是在帮别人隐瞒
You better not be covering for anybody.
我没有啊  学校里的大多数人都无视他
I'm not. Most kids at school ignore him,
而女生们全都觉得他很萌
and the girls all think he's cute.
还挺烦的
It's kind of annoying.
我希望你能照顾他
Well, I need you to look after him.
为什么
Why?
因为我是你妈  而我现在在好好拜托你
Because I'm your mother, and I'm asking you nicely.
如果我不想呢
What if I don't want to?
我不管  让你做就做
I don't care, you're doing it.
这怎么好好拜托了
How was that nice?
当时我在城市上空飞翔
So there I was flying above the city,
但当我醒来后  我发现自己不能飞
but when I woke up, I couldn't fly.
就像是你上次梦到自己跟女神麦当娜交往
That's like the dream you had where you were dating Madonna,
结果梦醒后  发现并不是真的
but when you woke up, you weren't.
没错
Exactly.
那你梦过自己的牙齿在一颗颗掉吗
You ever have the ones where your teeth are falling out?
虽然说掉牙好过掉发啦  但...
Better my teeth than my hair, but...
-谢尔顿  -在这里
- Sheldon? - Over here.
-你在干嘛  -躲着
- What are you doing? - Hiding.
躲谁
From who?
欺负你的人就是比利吗
Is Billy the one giving you trouble?
不是
No.
是他爸爸吗
His dad?
也不是
No.
不是吧
No...
她就是个恶魔
She's a demon.
斯巴克斯家的小女儿吗
The little Sparks girl?
你开玩笑吧  感觉很乖的小女孩啊
You're kidding. She seems so sweet.
他说她打他  还抢他的午餐钱
He says she slaps him around, takes his lunch money.
还往他衣服里扔蝌蚪
She even put a tadpole down his shirt.
可怜啊  这孩子衣服都是扎裤子里的
Poor kid, he tucks in those shirts.
-她看起来人畜无害啊  -她很可爱
- She looks harmless. - She's cute.
这样做坏事就很容易逃过责难
So she probably gets away with stuff.
我就像这样
I'm like that.
真好奇会不会有野猫把那里当猫砂用
I wonder if stray cats poop in that sandbox.
乔治
George.
你得去跟她家长谈谈
You need to talk to her parents.
我吗  为什么要我去
Me? Why me?
因为你比我更吓人啊
Because you're more intimidating than me.
这话她也好意思说
That's rich.
比利
Hey, Billy.
你好  米希的爸爸
Hello, Missy's dad.
-你爸爸在家吗  -在
- Is your father home? - Yes.
能去帮我叫他来吗
Could you get him for me?
没问题
Happy to.
爸爸  米希的爸爸来了
Dad, it's Missy's dad!
他也是谢尔顿的爸爸
He's also Sheldon's dad!
你好啊  邻居
Well, howdy, neighbor.
你好啊  赫谢尔
Hey, Herschel.
怎么来了  是鸡太吵了吗
What brings you by? Chickens too loud?
-没  它们挺好的  -那就好
- Nah, they been fine. - Good, good.
上周把吵的那只炸了
Fried up the noisy one last week.
这样它就安静了  所以今天来是有什么事呢
That shut him up. Anyway, how can I help?
这个嘛...
Uh, well...
我最近刚知道一件事...
It's come to my attention that, uh...
谢尔顿跟你们家女儿有点问题
Sheldon's run into a bit of trouble with your daughter.
什么问题
What kind of trouble?
谢尔顿说她总打他
He says she been beating on him.
-我们家芭比吗  -是的
- My Bobbi? - Yeah.
就是我家这个六岁的闺女
This one? The six-year-old?
芭比  你过来
Bobbi, get over here!
你知道我拉过比这孩子还大的屎吧
You realize I've taken dumps bigger than this kid.
-爹地  -乖女儿
- Hi, Daddy. - Hey, babydoll, uh,
库珀先生说你欺负他们家谢尔顿
Mr. Cooper says that you've been picking on Sheldon.
-这是真的吗  -不是的  爹地
- Now, is that true? - No, Daddy.
确定吗
Are you sure?
行吧  去洗手准备吃晚饭
Okay, go wash up for dinner.
我不知道了  乔治
I don't know what to tell you, George.
你觉得会不会有可能
I mean, is it, is it possible
是你儿子有点暗恋她
your son has a little crush on her?
我感觉他应该没这个办法
Oh, I don't think he's wired that way.
你是说他是同...
Oh, are you saying that he's a...
不是  我的意思是他就是个书呆子
No, no, I'm saying he's a bookworm.
除非她是数学或是字典  不然他应该没兴趣
Unless she's math or a dictionary, he ain't interested.
谢谢你听我说这事情
Thanks for hearin' me out.
是你老婆叫你过来的吧
Your wife sent you over here, didn't she?
我不想谈
I don't want to talk about it.
肯定是她
I bet she did!
我不想说
Not talkin' about it!
帮我跟她问个好
Tell her I said hi!
怎么样了
How'd it go?
挺好的
Uh, good. Yeah.
我处理好了
I handled it.
谢天谢地
Oh, thank the Lord.
是啊  谢我跟老天吧
Yeah. Me and the Lord.
我们合作的成果
Team effort.
芭比  你好
Hello, Bobbi.
你告我的状
You told on me.
其实是我哥哥想出来的
Well, actually, my brother figured it out,
所以严格来说  我觉得我没告发你
so, technically, I would argue that I didn't.
这不重要
Doesn't matter.
我应该告诉你
Uh, I should let you know,
我看了一本讲柔道的书
I've read a book on jiu-jitsu.
我准备好拿这本书丢你了
And I'm prepared to throw it at you.
谢利  这只是急救喷雾
Shelly, it's just Bactine.
我都还没涂到你身上
I didn't even put it on you yet.
你想告诉我发生什么事了吗
You want to tell me what happened?
芭比·斯巴克斯到车库里来了
Bobbi Sparks came into the garage...
她袭击你了吗
And she attacked you?
没有  我试图用柔道对付她
Not exactly. I tried to use jiu-jitsu on her,
但我绊倒了
but I tripped and fell.
宝贝  你得面对这些  我很抱歉
Aw, baby. I'm so sorry you're havin' to deal with this.
没关系
It's okay.
德国哲学家弗里德里希·尼采说过
German philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche said,
"但凡不能杀死你的  最终都会使你更强大"
"That which does not kill us makes us stronger."
你觉得自己更强大了吗
And do you feel stronger?
没有
No.
膝盖怎么样了
How are the knees?
好多了  谢谢
Better, thank you.
那就好
Good.
至于柔道这件事  你该知道
And regarding this jiu-jitsu stuff, you should know
男人不应该对女人动手
that a man's not supposed to raise his hand to a woman.
我不会的  我不想又伤到自己
Oh, I won't. I don't want to hurt myself again.
你小时候遇到过恶霸吗
Did you ever have a bully when you were growing up?
你见过你姥姥了吗
Have you met your grandma?
你不是说邻居的事你处理好了
I thought you said you handled it next door.
我是那么说过
I did say that.
你要去哪儿
Where you goin'?
去处理此事
To handle it.
一开始就应该由你出面
Should've been you in the first place.
什么
What?
祝好运
Good luck!
真棒  史酷比  不愧是我的新闻狗仔
Way to go, Scooby! That's my newshound!
米希  我很需要你的帮助
Missy, I could really use your help.
帮什么
With what?
我被芭比·斯巴克斯欺负
I'm being bullied by Bobbi Sparks.
笑死人  继续说
Hilarious. Go on.
妈妈说男人绝对不可以打女人
Mom says a man should never raise his hand to a woman.
但我想  我找到了空子可钻
But I believe I've found a loophole.
你是女人  所以你可以尽情揍她
You're a woman, so you're allowed to hit her as much as you want.
我为什么要揍她
Why would I do that?
因为我愿意付钱给你
Because I'm willing to pay you.
多少钱
How much?
我毕生积蓄  4美刀
My life savings, four dollars.
这是个好开始
That's a good start.
现在我们再来谈谈电视使用权
Now, let's talk TV privileges.
你想怎么样
What do you want?
接下来的两个月  每天下午看什么都由我决定
Complete control every afternoon for two months.
《质子教授》就是在那个时段播出
That's when Professor Proton is on.
我知道  你真惨
I know. Sucks for you.
我可牛逼了
I'm on fire!
你好啊  布兰达
Hello, Brenda.
你好  玛丽
Oh, hey, Mary.
你要开几条道
How many lanes you need?
其实我是有话要跟你说
Actually, I'm here to talk to you.
我们的孩子之间好像有点小问题
Seems that our kids are havin' a little problem.
对  赫谢尔告诉我了
Yeah. Herschel told me.
好  那就好
Oh, good, good.
我想知道你打算如何处理
So, I was wondering what you're plannin' to do about it,
因为情况好像没有任何好转
'cause the situation doesn't seem to be gettin' any better.
如果你还没注意到
Well, if you haven't noticed,
我正工作呢
I'm at work right now.
我看出来了
I see that.
但你知道
But you understand
你女儿在欺负我儿子吧
that your daughter's being abusive to my son.
或许你儿子需要长点胆子[蛋蛋]
Well, maybe your son needs to grow a pair.
等时候到了  他会的
And in due time, he will.
但现在  我请你
But right now, I expect you
教好你孩子如何做人
to teach your children how to behave.
康妮·塔克请到前台来
Connie Tucker to the front desk, please.
康妮·塔克
Connie Tucker.
你干嘛呼叫她
Why are you calling her?
你说我女儿在骚扰你儿子
You say my daughter's harassing your son.
她女儿也在骚扰我
Well, her daughter's harassing me.
玛丽
Hey, Mary.
你怎么来了
What are you doin' here?
我本来希望能理智地跟她谈谢利的事
Well, I was hopin' to have a rational conversation about Shelly,
但表现理智的人只有一个
but there's only one person being rational.
而那人不是你
Uh, and it ain't you.
我们先失陪一下
Could you excuse us for just a minute?
你知道你现在所处的地方
Do you understand that you are in the place
我每周都要在这社交三到四天吗
where I socialize three to four days a week?
你觉得保龄球比你外孙还重要吗
So you care more about bowling than your grandson?
当然不是  我只是说
Of course not. I'm just saying
也许有更好的解决方法
maybe there's a better way to go about it.
我提醒你  布兰达可是个恶毒的...
Now, I'm warnin' you, Brenda is one mean--
我不知道你不喜欢脏话
I know you don't like bad language,
但我们正在保龄球馆...  恶毒的婊子
but we are in a bowling alley-- one mean bitch.
我也可以很恶毒
Well, I can be mean, too.
你给我听好了
Okay, you listen to me.
你叫你孩子规矩点  否则我...
You get your kid in line or I...
你这是干什么
What are you doing?
滚出去
Get out of here.
这里是我做生意的地方
This is my place of business.
现在我知道你女儿是学了谁了
And now I see where your daughter gets it.
知道吗
You know what?
从你们一家搬进来那天起
I have been nothin' but nice
我一直都对你们礼貌有加
to you and your family since the day y'all moved in,
但我不会再那样了
and I'm over it.
看着你圣气逼人地走来走去
Watching you walk around all holier than thou,
觉得自己比其他人都优越
like you're better than everyone else.
你猜怎么着
Well, guess what,
你才没有
you're not.
老娘会狠狠地为你祈祷
I'm gonna pray for you.
她总对我那么说
She says that to me all the time.
我都不知道她是否真会那么做
I'm not even sure she does it.
进行得怎么样
How'd it go?
我不想说这事
I don't want to talk about it.
那是松木消毒剂的味道吗
Is that pine?
我们不说这个
We're not talkin' about it.
你去开门
And you get that!
赫谢尔
Herschel.
你好  乔治
Hey, George.
我最近刚知道一件事...
It has come to my attention
你老婆去我老婆工作的地方找她了
that your wife went to speak with my wife at her place of work,
-然后...  -她派你来这的吗
- and, uh... - She send you over here?
重点是  我来这是要告诉你
Uh, the-the important thing is that I'm here to tell you
玛丽的行为很不恰当
that, uh, Mary's behavior was inappropriate.
挺有意思的
You know, it's interesting.
我去你家时  你笑脸相迎
When I came to your house, you were laughin',
现在
and...
你却板着一张脸
now you're all serious.
为什么呢
Why is that?
我们到更自在的地方谈
What do you say we go talk about this
你说怎么样
somewhere a little more comfortable?
在门口的是谁
Who's at the door?
你请自便
Make yourself at home.
老天
Oh, boy.
你都在这消磨时间吗
You hang out in here?
是的
Sure.
一旦习惯了这股味儿
Once you get used to the smell,
这里还不太糟
it's not so bad.
我是高中橄榄球队教练
I coach a high school football team.
这里闻起来像牵牛花般清新
This smells like petunias.
我喜欢...
I like to...
暂时躲开家人
take a break from the family and...
到这里来看比赛
come out here and watch the games.
你老婆不介意吗
Your wife don't mind?
她不知道
She don't know.
她怕死鸡了
She's scared to death of chickens.
-是吗  -我一知道
- Is that right? - Once I found out,
就立刻决定建这个鸡舍
buildin' this coop was a no-brainer.
你去了好久
You were gone so long.
进行得怎么样
How did it go?
这个嘛
Well...
加一块糖还是两块
One lump or two?
两块  谢谢
Two, please.
比利呢
Billy?
我为什么要喝甜的茶
Why would I want lumpy tea?
他多美啊  对不对
Isn't he pretty?
美呆了
Very pretty.
我感觉自己很美
I feel pretty.
我处理好了
I handled it.
太谢谢你了
Thank you so much.
我们是一家人  应该的
We're family. It's what we do.
真不好意思  我老婆到保龄球馆去了
Listen, I'm sorry my wife went down to the bowling alley.
拜托  我才不好意思  布兰达逼我去你家
Please, I'm sorry Brenda made me come to your door.
我倒不介意
I'm not.
这是我一星期以来最开心的一天了
This is the most fun I've had all week.
孩子们有矛盾  我心里也不好过
I-I feel bad about the whole thing with the kids.
这常有的事
Hey, it happens.
我知道  但芭比不应该那样欺负谢尔顿
I know, but Bobbi shouldn't be beatin' on Sheldon like that.
-那是不对的  -真正不对的
- It's not okay. - What's not okay
是谢尔顿竟然被一个小女孩欺负
is Sheldon gettin' beat up by a little girl.
这个嘛
Well...
也对啦
Yeah.
我会跟芭比谈谈
Look, I'll talk to Bobbi.
不知道会不会有帮助  但我会尽力
I don't know if it'll help, but I'll try.
你是个好人
Hey, you're a good man.
我该回去了
Yeah, I-I should be headin' back.
好的  随时欢迎你来
All right, well, look, come on by anytime.
好
Yeah.
我们最好先把故事编圆
You know, we should probably get our stories straight
再跟我们各自的...
before we talk to our respective...
-伴侣说  -好
- mates. - Sure.
你想说什么
What do you want to say?
这个怎么样
How 'bout this?
我们发生争吵
We had words,
场面差点变得难看
it almost got ugly,
但我们最终达成了共识
but we came to an understanding.
-我喜欢  -嗯
- I like that. - Yeah.
你想打我一拳吗
You want to take a swing at me?
好看起来更真实
Make it look real?
我忍痛能力高得离奇
I have a freakishly high tolerance for pain.
不了  但你的提议有心了
No, no. But you're sweet for offering.
-晚安了  -晚安  哥们
- You have a good night. - You, too, pal.
赫谢尔
Herschel!
你特么在哪儿
Where the hell are you?!
我在底下建了个藏身洞
I built a hidey-hole under here,
但只够我们一个人躲进去
but there's only room for one of us.
那个蠢肥猪到哪儿去了
Where is that fat dumbass?
信不信由你  但那表示我今晚有艳福了
Believe it or not, that means I'm gettin' lucky tonight.
你们的婚姻关系好奇葩
Y'all have an odd relationship.
爱是一件神秘的事
Love is a mysterious thing.
赫谢尔
Herschel!
在充满捕食者的世界生存  不是易事
Existing in a world of predators isn't easy,
但我们猎物发展出了一些自然防御机制
but we prey have developed several natural defenses
帮自己活下来
to help us survive.
有装死
There's playing dead,
警告的大叫  伪装
warning calls, camouflage...
还有  最后一点也很重要的
...and, last but certainly not least,
传统老派的落荒而逃
good old-fashioned running away.
伴随着一点尖叫也无伤大雅
A little screaming never hurts either.